Finding Aid for West Michigan Environmental Action Council Records, 1968-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
West Michigan Environmental Action Council Records 1968-2005
West Michigan Environmental Action Council.
85504 Bn 2
Grand Rapids, Michigan-based environmental protection organization. Administrative, educational, legislative, and litigation files relating to various environmental issues, notably the Pigeon River Country State Forest oil drilling controversy, the problem of solid waste disposal, land and water use, and nuclear energy; contain files of executive directors Joan Wolfe, Roger Conner, Kenneth Sikkema, Frank Ruswick, Jr., Robert Newberry and Thomas Leonard.
19.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the organization (donor no. 6700 ) beginning in 1994. Subsequent additions have been received.
The record group is open to research.
Founded in 1968 as a non-profit organization by Mrs. Joan Wolfe and other concerned citizens, the West Michigan Environmental Action Council (WMEAC) was established to protect and restore the quality of Michigan's environment. By means of programs of education, legislation, and litigation, WMEAC worked toward the goal of "translating concern into action."
Throughout the 1970s, as the membership of the organization grew, so too did the number of legislative initiatives and court cases in which WMEAC was involved. During the tenure of Mrs. Joan Wolfe, executive director from 1968 to 1973, the membership grew to seven hundred individuals and sixty Grand Rapids civic and professional organizations. The budget of the organization in this period was $60,000. By 1978-1979 the budget had expanded to $100,000 and membership numbered eight hundred and fifty individuals and seventy civic and professional organizations.
Originally WMEAC focused its attention on the Grand Rapids and Kent County area. However, the leaders of WMEAC realized that the environmental issues of concern to the Grand Rapids area were identical to problems being faced in other parts of the state. As a result, the leadership decided to establish a series of statewide coalitions and committees of organizations and individuals sharing similar environmental goals. The resulting coordinated effort of similar-minded organizations and individuals was able to produce more effective legislative and legal action in environmental problem areas.
The rapid expansion and growing diversity of the scope of WMEAC's activities produced a need for more organizational flexibility. Thus, in 1971, WMEAC established two separate tax deductible foundations to aid them in their work. The Michigan Environmental Protection Foundation (MEPF) was organized for the purpose of engaging in environmental litigation; and the WMEAC Education Foundation was created for the purpose of educating the public to environmental issues and problem areas. The budget for the Michigan Environmental Protection Foundation was drawn from donations specifically solicited to carry forward certain legal suits. The MEPF was commissioned to choose its lawsuits carefully in order to establish precedents and lay important groundwork in the field of environmental law.
In 1973, Mrs. Joan Wolfe was appointed to the Department of Natural Resources' Natural Resource Commission by Governor William Milliken. Succeeding Mrs. Wolfe as the executive director was Roger Conner, a graduate of the University of Michigan Law School. While in school Conner and some of his fellow law students had organized the Environmental Law Society. He also served as a research assistant to Professor Joseph L. Sax, the author of Michigan's Environmental Protection Act of 1970. Conner became the first full-time executive director of WMEAC. During his tenure, WMEAC involved itself more in court actions and sought in this fashion to support the progress made through legislation.
Conner left WMEAC in 1978 and Kenneth Sikkema, a native of Cadillac, Michigan, replaced him. Sikkema had been a legislative assistant and this experience had given him a knowledge of legislative personnel and procedures helpful to WMEAC in maintaining effective channels of communication with the state legislature. During Sikkema's tenure, several important pieces of environmental legislation supported and sponsored by WMEAC were passed by the state legislature. Among these were the Solid Waste and Hazardous Waste Act (1979) and the Wetlands Protection Act (1979). Significant new programs were also created by WMEAC during this period such as the Michigan Used Oil Recycling Program (MUORP) in 1979, and the establishment of a coalition of Michigan environmental groups called the Michigan Environmental Council (MEC) in 1980.
Throughout the 1980s and early 1990s WMEAC continued to play a vital role in both local and statewide environmental education, litigation and legislation. During this period, however, the group's emphasis shifted away from direct involvement in environmental lawsuits and towards more of a public "watchdog" to monitor actions and decisions in private and public sectors that could have an impact on West Michigan's environment, and to alert the community to potential environmental harm. WMEAC fulfilled this role through representing environmental concerns behind the scenes in local, state, and federal governmental offices; providing informed testimony at public hearings, commission meetings, in the legislature and before judicial bodies; and intervening directly to protect the environment through litigation and legislation when necessary.
As public environmental awareness continued to grow throughout this period and environmental battles became more intensified and polarized, WMEAC continued to promote itself as a moderate organization which provided a "grass-roots" reflection of the West Michigan community itself. WMEAC thus endeavored to build coalitions with diverse interests in order to find "common ground" solutions to environmental problems rather than pursue radical activism. This approach proved highly successful as WMEAC achieved numerous significant accomplishments and launched several important new programs under the leadership of executive directors Frank Ruswick, Jr. (1982-1987) and Robert Newberry (1988-1992).
With the departure of Ken Sikkema in September 1982, Frank Ruswick, Jr. was chosen by the Board of Directors to become WMEAC's new executive director. Ruswick, a University of Michigan Law School graduate, left his post as Attorney Advisor in the U.S. Department of the Interior's Division of Conservation and Wildlife, and accepted the position. Under his tenure, WMEAC expanded its sponsorship of Michigan's first used motor oil recycling program (MUORP), extending its scope from its West Michigan headquarters to cover virtually the entire state. As the Michigan legislature continued to balk at constructing a state-funded program, WMEAC by default became the organizer of this ambitious privately-run program, which provided the only recycling sources for "do-it-yourself" oil disposal in the state. Due to constraints upon WMEAC's financial and other resources this program was able to recover only a small portion of the used motor oil dumped by "do-it-yourself" oil changers. The program, however, raised awareness statewide of the need for a government-funded recycling effort to address this problem. Other major programs developed by WMEAC during this era included a two-year project to work cooperatively with the West Michigan industrial and agricultural communities to reduce "nonpoint source" pollution of lakes and streams, development of an annual "Youth Conference on the Environment," and creation of a "Speaker's Bureau," a committee of volunteers and staff available to speak on environmental issues for area schools, organizations and groups.
Several important pieces of environmental legislation were also enacted as a result of WMEAC's activities during the directorship of Ruswick. The most significant of these legislative victories included passage of the Surface and Underground Mine Reclamation Act (1982), the Great Lakes Oil Drilling Ban (1982), the Peat Mining Act (1984), and the statewide ban on the use of the pesticide Chlordane (1987).
Ruswick resigned in October 1987 to accept a position as chief of Michigan's Civilian Conservation Corps, and Robert Newberry, then a WMEAC program specialist and pesticides expert, was named acting executive director. Newberry, a longtime Grand Rapids resident and graduate of Grand Valley State College with a degree in environmental science, was officially appointed executive director in January 1988, and under his leadership WMEAC continued its legislative success and developed several new programs which further expanded the scope of the group's influence both locally and statewide.
Most notable among the new programs established by WMEAC during Newberry's tenure were "YIKES!" (Young Idealistic Kids with Environmental Sensitivity - 1989), Designs for Environmental Awareness (1989), the Adopt-A-Stream Program (1991) and Project Greenspace (1992). YIKES! was established as a WMEAC-sponsored high school group and has engaged in such activities as Christmas tree recycling, letter-writing campaigns and making recycled paper. Designs for Environmental Awareness was a grant-funded program created to extend community awareness of local environmental concerns and efforts through consultations and workshop applications. The Adopt-A-Stream Program is an ongoing project which enables school, service, church and community organizations to "adopt" West Michigan streams in order to protect water quality and wildlife habitats. Project Greenspace was created to identify, protect and connect parks, fields, gardens and wooded areas which exist within West Michigan urban landscapes.
As always, WMEAC was very politically active during this era and its success in helping to enact environmental legislation continued unabated. Notable accomplishments included the Statewide Sewer Overflow Policy (1988), the Used Oil Dumping Ban (1990), Polluters Pay (1990), and the successful campaign of environmental groups led by WMEAC to block Governor Engler's proposed shakeup of the Department of Natural Resources, which would have eliminated many of the DNR's boards (1992).
With the resignation of Newberry in September 1992, the Board of Directors culminated a five-month, nationwide search with the selection of Dr. Sandra Marlatt as its new executive director. Marlatt, a Grand Rapids native whose diverse background includes teaching at Michigan State University, marketing county parks for the Kalamazoo County Visitors and Convention Bureau and running a 1,600-acre nature center in Nebraska, was commissioned to engineer the fulfillment of the goals of a five-year strategic plan enacted by the WMEAC Board of Directors in 1991. This plan calls for the establishment of ecosystems land use planning, the creation of strategies/programs to control non-point source water pollution and reduce toxic air emissions in West Michigan, and efforts to increase WMEAC's endowment fund by $500,000 and membership to 5000 by 1996.
Martlatt's tenure was short, and WMEAC went through several leaders over the next few years. Thomas Leonard, who considers himself more of an administrator than an environmentalist, took over the leadership role in 1995.
The projects Leonard has been involved with include the US-31 Bypass, Kent County International Airport, and the Nordhouse Dunes litigation. He has also been a member of several committees with work related to WMEAC's mission. One such group is the West Michigan Sustainable Business Forum.
New Working Groups have continued to be formed. The Religion, Ecology, and Spirituality group has been active planning Earth Day celebrations, and other such activities.
WMEAC has applied for grants to fund a number of initiatives, and both the Board of Directors and Leonard have taken an active interest in the retention and recruitment of members, as well as insuring the continued financial solvency of the organization.
"Action Issue", WMEAC's primary publication continues to be published monthly, providing news and information related specifically to the group, and to environmental issues in general.
The records of the WMEAC, received in multiple accessions, but now melded together, have been retained in an order approximate to that maintained by the organization in its earlier years. The records include administrative, educational, legislative, and litigation files relating to various environmental issues, notably the Pigeon River Country State Forest oil drilling controversy, the problem of solid waste disposal, land and water use, and nuclear energy; contain files of executive directors Joan Wolfe, Roger Conner, Kenneth Sikkema, Frank Ruswick, Jr., Robert Newberry and Thomas Leonard. the records are organized into eight series: administrative files, educational files, legislative files, litigation files, chlordane ban efforts, WMEAC non-serial publications, WMEAC publicity and media coverage, and WMEAC serial publications.
Subjects:
Nuclear energy.; Citizens' associations--Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Global warming.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Land use--Michigan.; Lubricating oils--Recycling.; Pesticides--Environmental aspects--Michigan.; Pigeon River Country State Forest (Mich.); Recycling (Waste, etc.)--Michigan.; Refuse and refuse disposal--Michigan.; Water--Michigan.
Contributors:
Conner, Roger L.; Newberry, Robert E.; Ruswick, Frank.; Sikkema, Ken, 1951-; Wolfe, Joan.; Leonard, Thomas.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative files
  The Administrative Files begins with a miscellanea of annual reports, historical information, budget data, and correspondence. Within this grouping is a file entitled "Organizational and Historical" containing materials from the period 1982-1992. This file includes an agency history from 1982, lists of board members spanning WMEAC's entire history, information about WMEAC affiliate organizations, statements of objectives, and of special interest, a strategic plan authored by the board which projects WMEAC's future direction and major goals for the period 1992-1996.
  Among the most significant files in the Administrative series are: Board of Directors files, Executive Director files, Assistant Director file, Administrative Staff files, and Engineering/Planning Coordinator files, and Program Staff files.
  - Annual Reports 1972-2001 scattered, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Organizational and Historical Information 1982-1992 (Box 1)
  - Budget Data
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Strategic Plan (Box 1)
  - Endowment fund and Capital Campaign (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - Name controversy (MUCC) (Box 1)
    - Political-Ford, Hart, Vander Veen (Box 1)
  - Histories and operational policies of WMEAC (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors
    The Board of Directors files contain records produced out of the operations and regular meetings conducted by the WMEAC Board of Directors. The "Board Decisions" files contain annual summaries of the policies and strategic positions adopted by the board from 1975 to 1994 on issues such as new programs to be launched, educational efforts, and support of various pieces of environmental legislation and litigation. As such, the board decisions provide a valuable resource for tracking the evolution of WMEAC's stances on the environmental problems of the era which, unlike the meeting minutes, are not encumbered by routine administrative decisions and other procedural matters. The board's "Minutes," 1968-1992, provide insight into the reasons behind major policy decisions and the dynamics of the operation of the Board of Directors. Also included, interspersed within the official minutes, are committee and financial reports and budget summaries.
    - Board Decisions
      - 1975-1984 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 1)
      - 1988-1991 (Box 1)
      - 1992-February 1994 (Box 1)
    - Minutes
      - 1968-1977, 11 folders (Box 1)
      - 1978-1992, 25 folders (Box 2)
  - Executive Director files
    The Executive Director files, as well as the files of the Assistant Director, Administrative Director, Administrative Staff, Engineering/Planning Coordinator, and Program Staff primarily comprise correspondence, arranged chronologically, and produced through the various operations and responsibilities of the different positions of the WMEAC administrative staff. Only a sampling of routine membership correspondence is included in the record group. The great majority of the materials included are substantive and provide a view of the overall scope and depth of WMEAC staff activities. Most notable are the plethora of letters written by WMEAC staff to various members of local and state legislatures, government agencies and the governor's office in support or criticism of various governmental actions with environmental implications. The interplay between WMEAC staff and local communities, business interests, and civic groups is documented here, and WMEAC's coalition and consensus-building efforts and moderate tactics are also clearly displayed.
    - Conner, Roger L. correspondence 1977-1978, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Sikkema, Kenneth correspondence
      - 1979-1982, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Ruswick, Frank, Jr. correspondence September 1982-December 1984, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Ruswick, Frank, Jr. correspondence January 1985-October 1987, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Newberry, Robert E. correspondence November 1987-December 1990, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Martlatt, Sandra correspondence 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Leonard, Thomas correspondence 1995-2004, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Assistant Director files
    - Davidson, Marty correspondence January-November 1986, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Stoneman, Julie correspondence November 1986-1990, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Administrative Staff files
    - Lobbestael, Diane F. correspondence 1977-June 1980, 8 folders (Box 5)
    - Woudenberg, Ginger correspondence 1994 (Box 5)
    - Finch, Kathleen correspondence 1994-1996 (Box 5)
    - Allen, Jennie correspondence 1998-1999 (Box 5)
    - Reusch, Theresa H. correspondence 2002 (Box 5)
  - Board of Directors
    - Kiste, Stan correspondence 1994 (Box 5)
    - Schroder, Marion correspondence 1994 (Box 5)
    - Peterson, Thom correspondence 1996-1999 (Box 5)
  - Engineering/Planning Coordinator
    - Dauphin, Jeffrey L. correspondence 1977-1980, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Program Staff files
    - Pelc, Elaine, Water Quality Program Director 1992-1994, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Cary, Tom, Program Coordinator 1994-2004, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Kauffman, Karla, Community Organizer 2002-2003 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - 1994 (Box 5)
- Educational files
  The Educational Files consist of WMEAC committee records, as well as information pertaining to the various causes and issues the group has adopted over the years. In these files, there are important documents relating to the Pigeon River State Forest oil drilling controversy, the problem of solid waste disposal, land and water use, transportation, and urban renewal and growth.
  Within the Educational Files, also, are the papers of other organizations and groups allied with or involved with the WMEAC. These are included in the transportation, solid wastes, housing and zoning, and water committees' files. These organizations include the Community Development Citizen's Committee of Grand Rapids; the Kent County Road Commission; Citizens for the Improvement of M-37; the Grand Rapids and Environs Transportation Study; the Michigan Environmental Review Board; the Statewide Coalition for Balanced Transportation; the Environmental Protection Agency; the Michigan Coalition for Better Waste Management; Michigan Committee for Environmental Information; Recycle Unlimited; the West Michigan Regional Planning Commission; the West Michigan Shoreline Regional Development Commission; the Committee on Urban Homesteading of Grand Rapids; the Grand Rapids Riverbank Committee; the Grand Rapids Watershed Council; the Michigan Sea Grant Program; and the Michigan Water Quality Standards and Drain Commission.
  - Annual Report 1972 (Box 6)
  - Support Committees
    - Finance or fund raising committee
      - Accounting statements (Box 6)
      - Fund raising campaign (Box 6)
      - Tax data (Box 6)
    - Communications or publicity committee
      - Brochures (Box 6)
      - Newspaper articles 1973-1979 (Box 6)
      - Responses to periodical and newspaper articles (Box 6)
    - Planning or policy and procedures committee (Box 6)
    - Education committee (Box 6)
  - Transportation issues
    - City of Grand Rapids
      - Fountain Street (Box 6)
      - 44th Street (Box 6)
      - 6th Street (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
      - South Beltline (Box 6)
    - Coalition for Sensible Transportation Solutions (Box 6)
    - Grand Rapids Metro Transportation
      - Community Development Citizen's Committee (Box 6)
      - East Beltline Association (Box 6)
      - Guidelines for Development (Box 6)
      - Impact Analysis and Notification Ordinance (Box 6)
      - Lake Drive (Box 6)
      - Ottawa County-Grand Haven (Box 6)
    - Kent Airport, Tom Leonard Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Kent County Road Commission
      - Agendas and Board Meetings (Box 6)
      - Drafts of investigative report (Box 6)
      - Final report-part two (Box 6)
      - Final report-notes (Box 6)
      - Project check-off list (Box 6)
      - Project questionnaires (Box 6)
      - Project survey response "Masterfile" (Box 6)
      - Suggested investigation of road commission (Box 6)
      - 12 mile road (Box 6)
    - M-21 Environmental Impact Statement (Box 6)
    - M-27 and Climax-Fullerton Projects (Box 6)
    - M-37
      - Citizens for the Improvement of M-37 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence 1976-1979 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence Gov. Milliken 1976-1977 (Box 6)
      - Grand Rapids and Environs Transportation Study-GRETS
        - Annual Reports 1973, 1975 (Box 6)
        - Citizens Committee Resolution (Box 7)
        - Historical Background (Box 7)
        - Project 77 (Box 7)
        - Proposed GRETS Unified Work Program (Box 7)
        - Transportation Improvement FY 1976-1980, 1981-1983 (Box 7)
      - Maps (Box 7)
      - Michigan Environmental Review Board (Box 7)
      - Proposals for Improvement (Box 7)
      - Statistics (Box 7)
    - M-66 Filer Creek (Box 7)
    - M-131 and M-31
      - Correspondence 1975-1977 (Box 7)
      - Highway encroachment committee-HECC (Box 7)
      - Reports, maps, clippings (Box 7)
    - M-275; correspondence with EMEAC (Box 7)
    - Statewide Coalition for balanced transportation (Box 7)
    - Transportation sub-committee report, notes (Box 7)
  - Parks and recreation committee
    - Off Road Vehicles (Box 7)
    - Sleeping Bear Sand Dunes (Box 7)
    - State and national parks (Box 7)
  - Solid Wastes Committee
    - Dirty Dozen-12 worst Michigan landfills (Box 7)
    - Fleischman Foundation (Box 7)
    - Grant Proposal 208-EPA Water Quality (Box 7)
    - Love Canal (Box 8)
    - Michigan counties
      - Cass county-Milton Twp. (Box 8)
      - Kent county
        - Byron Twp. (Box 8)
        - Cascade Twp. (Box 8)
        - Grand Rapids City (Box 8)
        - Kentwood City (Box 8)
        - Landfills (Box 8)
        - NPDES Permit (Box 8)
        - Plainfield Township Landfill
          - Arguments and Index, 3 folders (Box 8)
          - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 8)
          - Cost (Box 8)
          - Environmental Impact Statement, 3 folders (Box 8)
          - Motion for Adjournment (Box 8)
          - Petition for Leave to Intervene (Box 8)
          - Proposals and Exceptions For Decision (Box 8)